Exercise sheet number ten, task number one.
This is similar to the task from last week.
The difference is that here we have the Petri
net and we need to make the reachability graph
ourselves. Then we have to indicate which
properties hold for the Petri net. Just
like last week, we have these two tables with the
properties and we have to provide justification.
Let's start creating the reachability graph.
The reachability graph is going to consist of
tuples with three components, just like this
one. The first one is going to represent S1.
The second one is going to represent S2.
The third one is going to represent S3.
So we have tokens in S1 and S2. This is why
we start with this tuple. One token here,
one token here. Of course, don't forget about this
arrow that indicates that this is where we start.
Let's try firing the first transition, the
transition t1. So we have a token here. This
means it's possible. If we fire it, we reach
this marking. Also you can fire t2 to go back
from this marking to the first marking, because t2
requires a token in S2, and we have tokens in S2.
From the first marking, you can also
fire t2 and you reach this marking
because you have the requirement for t2, which is
a token in S2. Also, you can go back by firing t1.
The same, you have the required tokens
for t1, which is just one token in S1.
Let's try firing t3 from this first marking.
For t3, what's required is a token in S1. Yes,
we have that. Then we'll reach this
marking. Firing t4 gives us this marking.
What does t4 require? It requires a token in
S2. Yes, we have that here. If you fire t4
while you have this marking, it is possible
because t4 requires tokens in S2. We have that.
Then you reach this marking, which already
exists, reachable from this way here.
Also with this marking, you can fire
t3 because you have the required
token in S1. Then you reach the already existing
marking (1,0,1). Between these two markings,
you can go back and forth because t1 and t2
will have the required tokens. So here for t1,
you need a token in S1. You have that already. For
t2 you need a token in S2, and you have that here.
From this marking, you can fire t4 because
t4 requires a token in S2, which we have,
and you reach this marking (0,0,2).
Finally, you can go from
this marking to this marking by firing t3,
because you have the required token in S1.
So how do we know that we are done with the
reachability graph? So far all of these steps,
everything that I did here, is correct, for
sure, because we only fired a transition
when we had the required tokens for it. How
do I know that I haven't missed anything?
Well, for this marking, for the first marking,
everything is fine because we have t1, t2, t3,
and t4. We have all of the possible transitions.
Everything is used. We fired all transitions.
What about this marking? So here we have t1. And
t1, as I said, is possible because we have the
required token, which is a token in S1. What about
t2? It seems like t2 is not possible. Let's check.
So t2 requires a token in S2, which we don't
have here. What about t3? We have t3. We've done
it already. What about t4? For t4 it requires a
token in S2, which we don't have. So this means
all possibilities are covered. The same goes for
all other markings. So I've done the work already.
For this marking, for example, we have t2 and
t4, but we don't have t3 and t1 going out of it.
That is because t1 requires a token in S1,
which we don't have, and t3 requires a token
in S1 as well, which we don't have. For this
marking, we don't have t2, we don't have t4,
because both of these transitions require
tokens in S2, which we don't have.
For this transition, we don't have t1 and we don't
have t3 because both of these transitions require
tokens in S1, which we don't have. Finally,
for this marking, nothing is possible. No
transitions can be fired because t1 requires
something in S1. We don't have anything in S1.
t2 requires something in S2 and we don't
have anything in S2. t3 requires a token in S1,
and t4 requires a token in S2. So we don't have anything
in S1 and S2. This is why this is a dead end.
Now we can use this reachability graph
to answer the questions of the tables.
First of all, this Petri net is not strongly live
because from this marking that I just mentioned,
there are no nodes in the graph that can be
reached by firing any transitions. So in other
words, just like I said, this is a dead end.
Nothing is coming out of it. No arrow is going
out. So it is sufficient to say this graph is
not strongly live because we have a deadlock.
Also, this Petri net is weakly live
because all of the four transitions,
t1, t2, t3, t4, occur in the graph. This
means all of them have been used somehow.
So here we have them, you can see t1,
t2, t3, t4, everything is mentioned.
But this Petri net is not deadlock-free because
there is this deadlock we discussed before. No
arrows are going out of this marking. This Petri
net is also not 1-safe, because for example,
this node here contains a value which is bigger
than one, or this node here, or here. So these
three nodes, they contain values which are bigger
than one. That's it. But this Petri net is bounded
because no node contains a value greater than c
= 2. So the biggest number we see here is two.
Or you can also justify it by saying the
graph is finite. Since we were able to
draw the graph and we finished
the work, the graph is complete,
this means it's finite, and this means it's
bounded. So these are all of the values possible.
All of these are numbers. There is no threes,
no fours, that's it. This is why it's bounded.